Register of the Romanian Subject Collection, 1940-2007
Hoover Institution Archives
Romanian Subject Collection,
1940-2007
82104
27 manuscript boxes, 9 oversize boxes, 1 videotape cassette (17 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Newspapers, other printed matter, election campaign literature, writings, internal government and communist party documents, and miscellany, relating to the Romanian economy; youth organizations; the history of Transylvania; national minorities in Romania; Hungarian, Soviet and Bulgarian historiography regarding Romania; the overthrow of the communist regime in 1989; and subsequent political conditions and election campaigns.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research, except for one folder in Box 1, which is closed until 2020 December.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1982.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Minorities--Romania.; Bulgaria.; Hungary.; Romania.; Romania--Historiography.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Transylvania--History.; Youth movement--Romania.; Romania--Economic conditions--1945-1989.; Romania--History--1944-1989.; Romania--History--Revolution, 1989.; Romania--Politics and government--1989-; Elections--Romania.; Video tapes.
Series Description
- SUBJECT FILE, 1918-1992 (Boxes 1-5)
  Pamphlets, leaflets, reports, programs, election literature, government and communist party literature, relating to Romanian history, economy, political life, youth organizations and ethnic minorities, overthrow of Communist regime and subsequent political conditions and election campaigns, arranged chronologically and then by subject
- PERIODICALS, 1990 (Boxes 6-11)
  Regular newspapers and other sporadic publications printed in the aftermath of the 1989 revolution representing various political groups
- MEMORABILIA, n.d. (Box 12)
  Communist party flag.
Container List
Please see card catalog for increments that may have been received since December 1994.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1918-1992
  - 20th Century
    - Emigres. Union of Free Romanians. Booklet relating to activities of the Union of Free Romanians, 1985 (?). In Romanian (Box 1)
    - Legionary Movement. Pamphlet by Sima Horia, Declarations of the Legionary Movement Concerning the Fate of the Free World and the Tragedy of the Rumanian People, 1968
    - Miscellany. Three studies by an anonymous author, 1980-1981, relating to the history of Transylvania, especially as an area of dispute between Romania and Hungary; national minorities in Romania; and Hungarian, Soviet, and Bulgarian historiography in relation to Romania. In Romanian.
      [RESTRICTED]
  - 1944-1989
    - Communist party propaganda
      - General
      - Political training manual for teachers
    - Economy. Pamphlets, leaflets, reports, programs of Romanian government and communist party relating primarily to various aspects of the Romanian economy and agriculture, 1985-1989. Includes economic plans for 1990. Mainly in Romanian (Box 2)
    - Political and social conditions. Government propaganda brochures and pamphlets relating to various aspects of political and social conditions in Romania and to Romanian foreign policy, 1985-1987. Includes report by Rand Corporation. In English and Romanian
    - Youth movement
      - Album on youth group expedition, Journal de Expeditie. Includes photos, n.d.(1981 ?). In Romanian
      - Pioneers. Organizatia Pionierilor Consiliul National. Bound materials related to 40th anniversary celebrations in 1989, 4 volumes (Box 3)
  - Revolution, 1989. Publications, flyers, letter, photo chronicle relating to the overthrow of the Nicolae Ceausescu regime, 1989-1990. In Romanian and English (Box 4)
  - 1989- (Box 5)
    - Constitution, 1991. Printed copy. In Romanian and English
    - Economy. Brochures, and press release, relating to economic conditions and investment opportunities in Romania, and to trade relations with the United States, 1992
    - Elections. Leaflets, flyers, posters, and party programs issued by various political parties for the elections. In Romanian
      - 1990
      - 1992
    - Miscellany. Flyer and newsletter, 1991, relating to activities of the Association for International Law and International Relations
    - Parties. Political programs
    - Gheorghe Ursu Foundation videotapes. Consists of two video documentaries relating to G. Ursu, Romanian engineer and poet killed by the Securitate in 1985 because of his anticommunist opinions.
- PERIODICALS, 1990
  - General (Box 6)
    - 22
    - 24 Ore
  - A
    - General
    - A Het
    - Acasa
    - Anul 2000
    - Ardealul, Cluj
    - Ardealul, Satu Mare
    - Azi Pentru Miine
    - Azia
    - Atitudinea
  - B
    - Bihari Naplo
    - Buna Ziua
  - C (Box 7)
    - General
    - Catavencu
    - Clujul Liber
    - Contemporanul
    - Contemporanul Ideea Europaana
    - Contrapunct
    - Convorbiri Literare
    - Crisana
    - Crisana Libera
    - Cuvintul
  - D
    - General
    - Desteptarea
  - E
    - General
    - Echinox
    - Eco
    - Economistul
    - Erdelyi Hirado
    - Europai Ido
    - Eveninmentul
    - Expres
    - Express Magazin
  - F (Box 8)
    - General
    - Faclia
    - Fapta
    - FaptaBanateana
    - Fiatal Forum
  - G
    - General
    - Gazeta de Vineri
  - H-J
    - General
    - Impact
    - Independent
    - Jelenlet
    - Journal Literar
    - Jurnalul Afacerilor
  - K-L
    - General
    - Kelet-Nyugat
    - Lumea Crestina
  - M
    - General
    - Magazin
    - Majomsziget
    - Mesager
    - Miine
  - N (Box 9)
    - General
    - Nu
  - O
    - General
    - Oblio
    - Observator Bucuresti
    - Opinia
    - Opus
    - Opinia Studenteasca
  - P
    - General
    - Panoramic Radio-Tv
    - Parlament
    - Patria
    - Phoenix
    - Piramida
    - Politia Romana
    - Plus
    - Pro-Europa
  - R (Box 10)
    - General
    - Robinson
    - Romania Literara
    - Romanul
  - S
    - General
    - Scaiul
    - Semnal
    - Strict Secret
    - Strada
    - Supliment
    - Szekely Ujsag
  - T (Box 11)
    - General
    - Tara
    - Timisoara
    - Timpul
    - Timpul Capitalei
    - Transportubile Romane
    - Tribuna
    - Trompf
  - U
    - General
    - Unitatea
  - V
    - General
    - Viata Capitalei
    - Vitorul Liberal
    - Volosag
  - Z
    - Z
- MEMORABILIA
  - Communist party flag, n.d. (Box 12)
- Incremental Materials (Box 13-28:)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described.